<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Mischief of dissensions, or, A perswasive to Dr. Stillingfleet, Dean of St. Pauls, together with his respondents, &amp;c. to a seasonable alliance from their literal war, shewing the danger thereof, especially at this ambiguous juncture of time and affairs.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A37542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R55</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12574156</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12574156</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63529</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A37542)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63529)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 314:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Mischief of dissensions, or, A perswasive to Dr. Stillingfleet, Dean of St. Pauls, together with his respondents, &amp;c. to a seasonable alliance from their literal war, shewing the danger thereof, especially at this ambiguous juncture of time and affairs.</title>
                  <author>A. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Kidgell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: A.E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63529:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63529:1"/>
            <p>THE Miſchief of Diſſenſions: OR, A PERSWASIVE TO Dr. Stillingfleet DEAN of St. PAULS, TOGETHER WITH His <hi>RESPONDENTS,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>TO A Seaſonable Alliance from their <hi>Literal War.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING The Danger thereof, eſpecially at this Ambiguous Juncture of Time and Affairs.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Kidgell</hi> at the <hi>Atlas</hi> in <hi>Cornhill</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:63529:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63529:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WE being at this preſent toſſed with various Perturbations, it muſt needs be very unſeaſonable to encreaſe our Calamity in being our own moleſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; this is ever dangerous, but now it ſeems deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, by reaſon of the thick Cloud of Popery threatning us; and how ſoon it will ſhower down on our heads we know not. Therefore the practick part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion muſt be chiefly in theſe times regarded, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring our utmoſt induſtry, ſeeming to call upon us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Seek it <hi>quaſi Via tutiſſima,</hi> as the <hi>ſafe</hi> way, and <hi>only</hi> way too, conducing to our Happineſs, without which we may to our Eternity dig for Felicity, but find nothing but that ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Mines are not in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> ground.</p>
            <p>But herein conſiſts the excellency of fraternal Amity, in that it exceedingly promotes the honour of God, in the diſappointment and detriment of our Enemies; and hence no wonder that evangelical injunction of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our is ſo oft inculcated, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Love one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:63529:3"/> which for theſe many years hath been laid aſide, as if Chriſtianity it ſelf had been out of date, and its redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reedification not endeavoured in our late Civil Wars with reſpect to religion, the unhappy occaſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was exhibited, in that ſtroke given in a <hi>Sermon Preached at Guild-hall Chappel,</hi> called <hi>The Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of Separation,</hi> which Sermon <hi>(it is feared)</hi> hath indeed done more Miſchief than good. No ſober con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering men, whether <hi>Conformiſts</hi> as well as <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> denying it to be otherwiſe than ill timed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing it to give our deadly Enemies, the Papiſts, incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, who doubtleſly cannot be otherwiſe than ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilerated at our Proteſtant Diſſentions, in that it gives them opportunity to proſecute their execrable Projects with the greater vigour and ſucceſs; it is therefore our needfull and indiſpenſable work, as we would expect the Benediction of God from above, Peace and Tranquility among our ſelves, in laying aſide theſe fruitleſs diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and utterly abandoning and for-ſaking them with that moſt juſt Excommunication, that <hi>we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God.</hi> So then let us in one bleſſed unanimous conſent joyn with one ſhoulder, to bear the burthen of Reformation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of Unity and Concord, the inſeparable compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of an hearty Reformation, which will tend to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and augumenting of our proſperity and felicity both Temporal and Eternal.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63529:3"/>
            <head>To my Worthy Friend <hi>S. P.</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OF late having found a diſmal and ſore Specimen of Contention in a Literal War, between Dr. <hi>Edward Stillingfleet Dean</hi> of <hi>Pauls</hi> and ſeveral of the Nonconformiſts; I fear Sir theſe Civil Warrs between our ſelves may produce evil Conſequences: for the fire of Proteſtant diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, eſpecially at this time kindled and blown up, may diſmally give the Popiſh party advantage to their deſigned ends of conſuming us, by adding fewel to the fire of their malice: but doubtleſs our Concord would be cool Water, tending to quench or put out that fire of Hell, much conducing to the flouriſhing of our Nation and Religion; for could I be willing to pawn my blood, that this much pleaſeth our Enemies, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſee us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Ears, that they may come in for a ſhare, yea, and a bloody one too.</p>
            <p>Therefore in my Judgment, better is it for us (eſpecially at this juncture of time) though in ſome things diſſenting, yet to unite, rather than break open a Gap, for our Enemies to enter at, and deſtroy us.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded that <hi>Certamen Religioſum</hi> is of all Wars the moſt dangerous; for as it diſturbs the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63529:4"/> mind, ſcandals Religion, hardens Infidels, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours God, it alſo frequently is the Incentive to the Field, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I could wiſh it were better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as alſo that the Doctor had forborn the firſt unhappy ſtroke: But Sir, alas! great evils uſually attend high Promotions, common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth us how hard a matter it is for a man to ſwallow the great Goblet of Promotion, and not to be choaked therewith: Indeed it will be matter of Solace to our minds, if we can ſay like <hi>Job,</hi> That <hi>Gold we have not made our hope, nor fine Gold our Confidence;</hi> but how difficult is it to have a copious affluence, and the Heart not had therewith? Then no wonder, <hi>that it is a very hard matter for a Rich man to be ſaved.</hi> For if affiance in Riches poſſeſſeth the Room of any mans Heart, it is a great evil, in that it ſtrongly inclines to conceit of our ſelves; an Impiety to which mans corrupt Nature is ſtrongly propenſe; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally amidſt plentifull fruition; which conceitedneſs tends to a contempt of our Brethren, which is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the eyes of a Pure God: For <hi>he is Love,</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>and he that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him;</hi> as alſo that of St. <hi>Paul, Love endureth all things.</hi> It is certainly a Grace of the firſt magnitude, very magnificent and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did, beautifull both in the eyes of God and man: But we had need be cautious, according as <hi>Paul</hi> moſt excellently and ſweetly adviſeth in <hi>Galat. chap. 5. ver. 15. If ye bite and devour one another, take heed that ye be not devoured one of another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leave it to any rational man, if Proteſtant Diſſentions be not the very road to Popiſh deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63529:4"/> their projects doubtleſs being embarked on theſe two bottoms, to debauch and divide us; at leaſt-wiſe, with diabolical Cunning to endeavour the Debauchery of the Wilder ſort, and the Diviſion of the Sober; that thoſe who only affect the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory of Divinity, may not want matter of diſpute, remaining ſtill reſtleſs, never attaining the practick part; and doubtleſly men only acquiring ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Notions, without any application, is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal reaſon why ſo many unorthodox Opinions are broached and imbibed, and the Judgments of others hereby corrupted, the Popiſh Party by divers cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning inſinuations aſſuming ſeveral ſhapes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, in matters relating to Religion, gradual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infuſe their own impious and ungodly princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. What ſhall we ſuppoſe of the Quakers, omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nominating any more, ſave the <hi>Arminians,</hi> which profeſſedly deny Popery, but upon my ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate Thoughts find them leaning towards it, as it were hanckering after the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt;</hi> their Opinions ſeeming to me as a Gate or inlet for Popery?</p>
            <p>And know we not by experience, that this both hath been and is the practice of the Jeſuites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to inſinuate themſelves eſpecially among the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the weaker illiterate ſort of People? As <hi>they enter not themſelves</hi> (I fear) <hi>into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, ſo are they likewiſe an impediment or hinderance to thoſe that would,</hi> if not ſometimes a Total obſtruction.</p>
            <p>And, Oh how fearfull a thing is it, Sir, for us to encourage theſe wicked Enemies of God, theſe ill-wiſhers to his Church, and dividers thereof!
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63529:5"/> this fire from Hell to conſume us (if God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent not); therefore it is time theſe Coals of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention be extinguiſhed, leſt they catch hold and conſume us.</p>
            <p>But if ſo be our Diſunion is ſo pernicious, ſo greatly complying with, and gratifying the evil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of our enemies, then certainly the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual way to be our own Friends, likewiſe to fruſtrate, and diſappoint the Projects and Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our deadly Enemies, is to unite in Love; and notwithſtanding there may be ſome diſſenſion in Judgment, not to let it grow ſo wide as to cauſe an abſolute difference in affection. Indeed I would deſire, and much would it conduce to our good, if theſe Jarrings were forborn, conſidering we are Brethren, and why ſhould we fall out by the way? and ſeeing on both ſides amongſt the Orthodox, there is no difference in fundamental Points.</p>
            <p>But he that gives the firſt ſtroke does worſt; <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens tacet,</hi> Truth muſt be defended, therefore a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber impartial Vindication can't be blamed; but there is a time for this: nevertheleſs in my thoughts the preſent time calls for our Divines to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to cut the Sinews of Popery, to bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter down the Walls of <hi>Babylon;</hi> Let us beware of temporizing, let not Promotion blind, or Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſſs byaſs; let no man confide in his Parts, Learning, Wealth or Dignities, but conſider <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion cometh neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, but from the Lord only;</hi> and if ſo, let us en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to find it be in mercy; for Wealth, and Promotion; may as well be a Curſe as a Bleſſing a Knife that is ſharp may be ſerviceable, but to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63529:5"/> cut our Throats withall, is greatly hurtful; a Sword by how much the keener, by ſo much the more excellent, but in the hand of a Mad-man by ſo much the more deadly.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>let Brotherly Love remain,</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Advice of the Bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>If a Brother offend, not to deſpiſe him, but in the Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to reſtore ſuch an one, conſidering with thy ſelf that thou mayeſt alſo be tempted.</hi> But alas poor frail Creatures that we are! how apt to deſpiſe an Erring Brother, and how little ſenſible of our own weakneſs, and how apt our frail Natures are to decline or turn aſide to our Enmity and Contentions which are very dangerous, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions which are Church-ruining! <hi>How lovely and pleaſant a thing is it then for Brethren to live to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unity!</hi> It is the new Commandment, yea, and a Command in ſpecial, and verily a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary eſſential part of true Chriſtianity; and doth not diſobedience to one Divine Command render us conſcious of breaking the whole? And if Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to our Brethren be an Evidence of one cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dially embracing <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> what then will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our <hi>Bibles?</hi> but if they which are <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Dei</hi> be true, it is an Evidence of an unholy unchriſtian temper.</p>
            <p>But alas how miſerable are we become through our various diviſions! how deſolate do we ſit! a thing greatly to be lamented; I find moſtly that our Differences are in Affection. In Judgment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63529:6"/> we have many, and really exceeding Erroneous, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Romiſts,</hi> to whom we neither ſeek, or or hope for Reconciliation, believing them to be in their vile Principles, irreconcileable to the very Law of God; endeavouring as it were practically to rend the Decalogue out of the Bible, by their wicked Principles of Impiety with reſpect to the firſt Table, and of Immorality in reference to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Antiſabbatarians</hi> pluck out to their power the fourth, notwithſtanding a <hi>Memento</hi> prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, as alſo fixed in the heart of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Antinomians</hi> they are for taking away the whole Law at once, denying it, and rendring it wholly uſeleſs to Chriſtians, whether as a Rule, or in it's coactive or punitive power.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Socinians</hi> alſo, a moſt dangerous and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Enemy, a dreadful diſturber of the Church, and Violator of the Goſpel, endeavouring with <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> to quench the <hi>Deity</hi> of the <hi>Son of God,</hi> deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo our Redemption by the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the high diſhonour of the riches of Gods Grace, and hurt of Souls, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to deprive us of the benefit of the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Antiſcripturiſts,</hi> who are the Enemies to the Scriptures, caſhiering both Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:63529:6"/>
            <p>And the <hi>Antitrinitarians,</hi> who are blaſphemers of the whole Trinity.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Familiſts,</hi> who leaving the ſure Rule of the Word, truſt to Satanical Deluſions.</p>
            <p>Not to leave the <hi>Separatiſts</hi> who abſent all publick Communion, pretending that for which they have no ground, <hi>viz.</hi> to live above Ordinances; Poor Creatures! becauſe they know not the marrow of them, they live above that which they know not.</p>
            <p>But theſe I wave, which, or moſt of which are far diſtant from the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whether as to the Conforming Orthodox party, who embrace the Pure Doctrine of the Book of Homilies, or as to their diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Non-Conformiſts. And therefore theſe moderate differences ought not to make immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate diſtances: But I muſt needs grant, that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Judgment frequently cauſeth alienation in Heart, and ſwelling of mind; and hereby do we ſee, that thoſe Friends who have been near allied, and held an intimacy of acquaintance, when they have come to claſh one againſt another in Opinions, have alſo forſaken their former intimacy, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently grown Enemies, in oppoſing and cenſuring each other: and by reaſon of this diſunion come ſo many Invectives in Pulpit and Preſs. For to tell the truth, in ſome Churches there is ſo much inveighing againſt their contrary Party, as that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63529:7"/> it hath amazed me to conſider, whether theſe men thought they had their Commiſſion from God to preach the Goſpel, or to declaim againſt a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular party of Proteſtants?</p>
            <p>But if ſo be that we are unanimouſly Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in the main, diſſenting only in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Opinions, in the holding and maintaining of which dependeth not Salvation or Damnation, is it not very unreaſonable, that the poor Souls attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Miniſtry ſhould be denyed the wholſom Bread of Life, and held to that Hay and Stubble which neither is Food ſuited to their Nature, or Nouriſhment? What good doth it any man on a Sabbath day to enter into the Church, and inſtead of a good practical Sermon, which tendeth through Gods grace to warm the Affections, and influence the Practice, to hear a ſpeech of Reviling or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the Diſſenters? if this perſon be one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to hear Gods Word, and regards the way <hi>ad vitam aeternam,</hi> I durſt be confident he approveth not hereof, this being the way rather to ſtarve than feed his Soul.</p>
            <p>Let there not therefore be ſuch Invectives in Pulpit and Preſs, which tend not to the profit of the good, but to incenſing the Malice of the bad; for hereby many are influenced to Raillery, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning others, but for what they underſtand not; only receiving and entertaining Prejudices, (which tend much to Gods diſhonour;) for it (through Satans ſubtility, and Natures horrid corruption)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63529:7"/> conduceth to an imbittered oppoſition of Religion and holy men, <hi>qua tales,</hi> as they be holy; and ſo conſequently if God beſtoweth not repenting Grace, they perſiſt in this height of Impiety, growing worſe and worſe, obdurated in evil, and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of good, till at laſt they become Veſſels of Gods fury and Wrath, as they have before ſold themſelves to the Vaſſalage and miſchievous drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery of the Devil.</p>
            <p>And others Heads are puzled about unedifying Controverſies and Debates, whileſt their Hearts are empty of the power of plain <hi>practical Divinity,</hi> and likely ſo to remain, becauſe unconcerned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, moſt miſerably prying into Religion more for <hi>Curioſity</hi> than <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it cannot be denyed, but that the good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt practical Divines of both Perſwaſions have, and do much eſteem each other, living and loving as Brethren; and whatever ſome may either ſay or act, it is my obſervation, never finding other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but a Sober Orthodox <hi>Conformiſt</hi> regarding, and entertaining good opinions of the <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> and ſo, <hi>è contrario.</hi> For as it is dangerous to impoſe upon other mens Conſciences, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it's not good or ſafe to condemn another, becauſe capable of acting ſome indifferent thing in it ſelf, notwithſtanding I diſſent herefrom, yet cannot but confeſs it not to be neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or dangerous of it's loſs; why then ſhould I judge and cenſure him as an Heretick, or a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63529:8"/> not worthy of having any Communion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>And verily, Sir, this Union in heart, and living <hi>in love</hi> as <hi>Brethren,</hi> is the way for Proteſtant Churches to flouriſh: let none be ſilenced, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, let all Proteſtant Miniſters unanimouſly joyn in preaching Chriſt in his Perſon, Offices, Merit and Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and not lye idle, in Jarring at one another; this is not the way for their Maſters work to be performed: <hi>Vae mihi ſi non Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zavero,</hi> ſayes that bleſſed induſtrious Apoſtle, who <hi>preached Chriſt in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, rejoycing that Chriſt was preached, although out of envy, as well as out of good will,</hi> and declaring his reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as to that his Heaven-ſpirited Joy, that <hi>he would rejoyce;</hi> ſo that the Intereſt of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> might be propagated, <hi>Paul</hi> would be pleaſed, and his Joy excited: But in order to it's more free courſe, Unity was found neceſſary, therefore ſhall we find him in tracing his Epiſtles as we read, exceedingly exhorting hereunto, and dehorting from Strifes, Envyings, Debates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now in <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Chap. 3. Verſ.</hi> 1. you ſhall find him calling them Fooliſh, <hi>O fooliſh Galathians,</hi> &amp;c. by reaſon of their Apoſtaſie from the Doctrine which he had taught and they embraced; but trace him down to the end of the Epiſtle, and you ſhall find him often calling them <hi>Brethren;</hi> which inſtructs us in a good Leſſon, <hi>viz.</hi> That in difference of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Opinion, let there be no diviſion in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; for it is a ſore temptation, and bait of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63529:8"/> the Devil, to raiſe alienation and averſation in the Affections, when he perceives the Opinions not agreeing: But Diviſion it is the deadly plague of the Church, mortally tending to it's overthrow and ruine. But the Church, which ſhould walk in conformity to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is Love, whoſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> alas! how does it, and hath it for theſe many years dreadfully dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, and thoſe therein profeſſing Memberſhip to <hi>Chriſt</hi> endeavoured to rend in pieces his Intereſt? But in all Ages he hath reſerved to himſelf faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Witneſſes, ſtanding up for his Glory and his Churches good; endeavouring our Peace and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the ſumme of Evangelical Obedience is Love, <hi>let us walk according to that Rule, that Peace may be upon us;</hi> how oft have we it repeated and inculcated upon us, <hi>Bear one anothers burthens, and be kind, be tender-hearted, forgiving one another,</hi> back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with this indiſputable incitement, <hi>becauſe Chriſt for Gods ſake hath loved you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, can we be ignorant, how grand a deſign <hi>Satan</hi> the deadly Enemy of the Church hath, to rend it with multitude of Diviſions, well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how effectual a way that is to ſuppreſs the encreaſe of the Goſpel, and to advance the intereſt of his Kingdom; moſt clearly diſcerning, that if we cloſely ſhould follow the moſt bleſſed counſel of the Apoſtle, <hi>viz. To be all of the ſame mind, to ſpeak the ſame thing,</hi> would be dangerous, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63529:9"/> he might have none of us: But that in this life, leading a life of ſimple Chriſtianity, <hi>at peace with God, and alſo among our ſelves;</hi> which is <hi>praeguſtus Coeli,</hi> even the foretaſte of Heavenly felicity, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in us an aptitude and meetneſs for the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of eternal Glory and Beatitude, as alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably conducting us in the way thereunto, to the ſorrow and vexation of our deadly Enemies, whether Satan, or his Children incarnate, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh party.</p>
            <p>But as we have Enemies without doors, working to their utmoſt the impeding of this happy Unity, ſo likewiſe have we within doors, that ſtrongly oppoſe it; and, as the uſual Proverb is, <hi>We enter the World with a Pope in our Bellies;</hi> we are naturally apt to be puffed up: it is well known that empty Veſſels give the greateſt ſound; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe empty men, who are unacquainted with Religion in it's Excellency and Power, having all unfurniſhed ſave a Head big with ſome giddy Notions of what the Heart affects not, together with ſome Learning, by which this ſpeculative Divine is puffed up, <hi>and whileſt he thinks himſelf to know ſomething,</hi> in reality <hi>knows nothing;</hi> and hence no wonder that oft ſuch men prove Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troublers.</p>
            <p>Others alſo conſcious of a Crime near a-kin and ſometime conſequent of the former, <hi>viz.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs, which much affects Singularity, by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a man oft rather to broach Heterodox Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63529:9"/> than embrace Orthodox; that ſome may be his followers, and it may be go <hi>ſuo nomine,</hi> with the Badge of his own Name, and ſo he become famous, or rather (to ſay truth) infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous.</p>
            <p>Others are turned aſide by Intereſt and the power of Unbelief, <hi>Demas</hi>-like, <hi>loving this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World,</hi> and prizing it as the Place of their Acquieſcence and Happineſs, Idolatrouſly loving Gold more than God, and (fooliſhly) a good Purſe better than a good Conſcience; not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctically minding, that the man that would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Salvation, muſt Ungod the World, not in <hi>thinking gain to be godlineſs:</hi> But although he in words and profeſſion may acknowledge a better good than this World, yet in Heart and conſent of the Will, embraces no other; no wonder, <hi>becauſe the God of this World blinds the mans eyes,</hi> inſomuch that ſelfiſh Intereſt ſhall turn him which way it pleaſes, this is indeed greatly I to be lamented!</p>
            <p>Others by the deceitfulneſs of Riches are choak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and temporize, in conforming to the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and Doctrines moſt in faſhion, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain or encreaſe their Honour, unwilling ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly to adhere to a deſpiſed Goſpel, and a perſecuted defamed Truth, not ſuppoſing <hi>Nuda Veritas</hi> will be a Covert to ſhelter them from the Cenſures of the great ones, or gratifie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Itch of Ambition, in tending towards higher Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63529:10"/> But, Sir, let them contemplate that thundering <hi>Menax</hi> in the Goſpel, <hi>He that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth me before men, him will I deny before my Father, and before the Angels of God.</hi> But oh how natural is it for man to ſet up his Riches for his God, and to fall down and worſhip them?</p>
            <p>Others by putting confidence in their Parts, Learning, Wiſdom, and Strength of Reaſon, are hurried and driven to Errors in Religion: for notwithſtanding Religion is not contrary to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet it is above it, fo far forth as it is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or humane, immenſly overreaching, ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſurmounting our poor ſhallow Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; hence the holy Apoſtle in 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> having ſeriouſly conſidered and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated the Decrees, Wiſdom and Counſell of God, how does he ſeem to abandon all his Reaſon, though certainly very perſpicuous, and fall into a Paſſionate admiration of the infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God? ſaying, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the Wiſdom and Knowledge of God! how unſearchable are his Judgments, and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when by ſhallow Reaſon, as all humane is in it ſelf conſidered, men would dive into Gods depths of Wiſdom and Counſel, oh how greatly are they deceived! what falſe Ideas of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on do they conceive, into what multitudes of Errors do they plunge themſelves, to their own
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63529:10"/> harm, to the Churches detriment and moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in their not reſting on Divine Revelation any further than it would ſuit with carnal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? I am perſwaded this hath much more damnified the Church than the Perſecutions of it's moſt malignant Oppoſers; it being a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhonouring, crediting him ſo, as no further to reſt in his Word than carnal Reaſon can fathom, it's Truth to believe no further than we can by our Reaſon and Wiſdom trace: Hence iſſued the moſt notorious Hereſies that ever infected the Profeſſing World. It is therefore a needful Maxim to make Gods Word our Rule; better is the moſt illiterate perſon making this Word his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, than the Learnedeſt Hero reſting in the validity of his Reaſon: And hence no wonder the Apoſtle makes this Challenge; <hi>Where is the wiſe? where is the Scribe? where is the diſputer of this World? God hath choſen the poor things of this World,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the things which are not, to bring to nought the things which are.</hi> God will have the Revenues of his Glory, and he will have no fleſh to glory in it ſelf; he will bring down the Pride of all fleſh one way or other: But let Reaſon have the place of <hi>Ancilla Pietatis,</hi> to be Godlineſſes Handmaid, and let Religion be the Miſtreſs, and have the preheminence, then Reaſon in it's due place is a noble and excellent gift and endowment, ſubſervient to Religion, and in that place it is a good Servant, but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a wicked Maſter.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:63529:11"/>
            <p>By theſe or the like means through the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid depravedneſs of Nature, and the deſperate corruption of Heart, men are ſeduced, blinded; and byaſſed; to prevent which, a heart circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed to love God is neceſſary, whence moſt ſweetly flowes mutuall Love to one another; for no man that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but will be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo: <hi>he that hateth his Brother, and yet ſaith he loveth God,</hi> we have a Divine warrant from the Word to call that man a Liar.</p>
            <p>Myſtical Union to Chriſt, and real Implan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation into him, is inſeperably accompanyed with fraternal Union: What, love the Head, and not the Members! it is verily impoſſible. Can a man be in Chriſt, and yet out with his dear Members? No certainly; Chriſts true Friend will never be his Members Enemy.</p>
            <p>The Holy Spirit inhabiting a mans Heart, even that Spirit of Love and Meekneſs which are the Fruits of that Holy Spirit, which certainly it will bring forth in that Garden where this bleſſed Wind bloweth: Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no Strifes, Diſſenſions, Heats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be fruits of this Spirit, I leave all to judge who ſhall peruſe this Paper.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, it is an eſſential part of the Church of Chriſt to be conformable to its Head, and certainly in ſome meaſure conformable to his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63529:11"/> Will are the true Members thereof, however the carriage of ſome ſelfiſh Pretenders to Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberſhip may be, whoſe intent may be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to devour than feed the Flock, but in this Cenſure (mentioning it onely by the way) without regard to any particular mans Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, I fear our late Literal Skirmiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Doctor, his Vindicators and Reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, has done us no great good; it hath not tended to beat down prevailing Popery; it hath not been of uſe to furniſh the minds of the People with Arguments againſt Popiſh Errours, in well grounding them in the Fundamentals of true Chriſtianity; a work exceedingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring and calling for all the Diligence, Parts, Learning and Induſtry of our Divines to be buſied about, ſeeming now to be as it were the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſarium,</hi> of indiſpenſible neceſſity; the Practical preaching up of Chriſt in his Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prieſtly, Prophetical and Kingly, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of all which are to the utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the Papiſts, yea and ruine too if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: But it is certain the Lord will maintain his Honour in ſpight of all oppoſition. And, Sir, how needful is it for our Divines <hi>to preach Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified?</hi> A ſuitable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine for this Juncture of time, wherein the diſmal Cloud of Popiſh Errors and Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons threatens to fall on us.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63529:12"/>
            <p>But ſuppoſing the Doctor is in very truth ſpeaking what the Non-conformiſts juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, (as one of his Admirers ſaid in my hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) yet it was unſeaſonable, and this pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gloomy ſeaſon required ſilence here, and an open Mouth againſt Popery. But I will wave that; <hi>Magna eſt Veritas &amp; praevalebit:</hi> I deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not when I began to write, to meddle with the preſent Controverſie, otherwiſe than to hint, of what I could not eſcape.</p>
            <p>But this I am <hi>in fine</hi> perſwaded of, let us warre, and fight, and jarre, and bite one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, we are hereby our own deſtroyers, and at laſt may be our own Butchers; and this time calls for a work of far greater neceſſity, and weighty importance, yea and the Concern thereof ſo exceeding ponderous, that if we thus continue, it may have a ſad end, and that ſo grievous, that our ſelves and Poſterities may have impoſed on us the Yoke of Popery, <hi>which neither our ſelves or Fathers have been able to bear.</hi> Which Yoke to prevent, let us unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly adhere to the Truth of the Goſpel, and with one ſhoulder bear the burthen of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; in order to which end let us be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to Unity, and dehorted from Diviſion; for us to expect a flouriſhing Nation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to trample on our Enemies, whileſt we continue in Strifes and Conteſts among our ſelves, is a thing impoſſible; but Union
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63529:12"/> makes this feaſable, yea and a thing with facility to be performed: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us, ſeeing Chriſts Body is a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Unity, that Spirit of Jeſus a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Love, according to the earneſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation of the Apoſtle, <hi>Endeavour to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of peace:</hi> See his Argument; <hi>For there is one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and one Spirit.</hi> It was Chriſts Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to his Father, Oh how Pathetick is that his Prayer in <hi>John</hi> 17<hi rend="sup">th,</hi>! <hi>That they may be one as we are one, that they all may be one, that they alſo may be one in us, that they may be made perfect in one.</hi> And this tendeth much to Gods glory, the Supream ultimate end of his true Worſhippers, according to that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 15<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God.</hi> And I cannot but mention another Scripture, very pertinent to the purpoſe; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10. wherein the bleſſed St. <hi>Paul</hi> does moſt earneſtly <hi>beſeech them, by the Name of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, that they all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no Diviſions among them, but that they be perfectly joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame mind, and the ſame Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And to the <hi>Philippians</hi> we ſhall find him preſſing it as the only thing to be deſired, coming in with an <hi>Only let your Converſation be as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, that whether I come to ſee you, or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63529:13"/> elſe be abſent, I may hear of your Affairs, that ye ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one Mind, ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel.</hi> And truly Sir, why ſhould the Apoſtle ſo adjure us to Unity, were it not of high Concernment to the Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtianity? for if we inſpect but his concluding Farewell to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> in the Second Epiſtle, <hi>Chap. 13. Verſ. 11. Finally Brethren, farewell; be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, live in peace, and the God of Love and Peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know not how great a Miſchief a little fire of Contention may do; it may verily encreaſe to more ungodlineſs: Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is the Devils Muſick, but it will cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in our ſorrow. But Unity it is Chriſts delight, let us follow it, becauſe Gods In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, <hi>Follow Peace with all men;</hi> and becauſe a branch of the Covenant of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>I will give them one heart;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an Evidence of a Diſcipleſhip to Chriſt; <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my Diſciples, if ye love one another:</hi> For which alſo we have the Practice of the Primitive Chriſtians for our Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; <hi>The Multitude of them that believed were of one heart, and one ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:63529:13"/>
            <p>And in ſhort, There is but one God, one Chriſt, one Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore, as the Wiſe man ſayes, let us hear <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum hominis,</hi> Fear God and keep his Commandments, and let us not waſte our inch of Time, troubling our heads about all the Controverſies in the world. We muſt know this for certain, that there's but one way left us for Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Let us hearken to the ſumme, <hi>He that believeth on the Son, hath Life, but he that believeth not on the Son, ſhall not enter into Life, but hath the wrath of God abiding on him.</hi> Again, <hi>He that would be my Diſciple, let him deny himſelf, take up his Croſs, and follow me:</hi> Here is no Gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſography, plain Terms, the Simple may underſtand it with facility, though the Wiſe cannot practiſe it without the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Omnipotent Grace, therefore our Duty is in leaving Diſputing to fall upon Practice.</p>
            <p>But how greatly is it to be bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and how dolorous a Complaint may we take up, in that we are circumvent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with multitude of erroneous Principles, and hereby the breach of Diviſion grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63529:14"/> wider and wider; and I profeſs, let what will be ſaid, That to teach us Wiſdom and Unity, God will ſend ſome ſevere Diſpenſation, and it is well if Gods Judgments are not impending over our heads for this our ſin; ſhall we then go on to provoke the Lord? Certainly he will vindicate his own Glory, when we have taſted by fearful Experience the ſmart of Gods Judgments for our Diviſions, and he hath let in our Enemies on us, and ſuffered our Fears to overtake us, and let us ſuffer together, then ſhall we certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cry, <hi>è bello Pax;</hi> No more Warre, we have experimented its evil, but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Peace ſhall return; but till God by an eminent Act of his Righteouſneſs <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth forth his hand, and executeth Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> there is little hope hereof, we being ſo greatly degenerated, and the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Diſeaſes of our Minds grown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veterate.</p>
            <p>But then, Sir, to conclude, how daring are we, when the Symptoms of our uineby the malicious intentions of our Enemies is preſaged, which through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant mercy hath been detected, and thereby hindred; to which Plotts, and Conſpiracies againſt our King, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63529:14"/> Perſons, and Religion, have we given much advantage, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by our Diviſions, yet hath God freely been Gracious ſtill in detecting and defeating them hitherto, and ſhall we be ſo fooliſh and unkind to God, as to ſtill perſiſt in our Iniquity, and as it were wilfully to draw down Judgements on our own heads, and provoke God to withdraw his protecting Providence from us?</p>
            <p>I would perſwade all men to Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>to the Higher Powers, for they be of God,</hi> and it is Gods will that <hi>we ſhould obey Magiſtrates, and not ſpeak evil of Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes;</hi> they are an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> and we highly advance Gods honour in eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſubmitting to his Ordinances; but Conſcience prohibiting what the Magiſtrate enjoyns, <hi>whom ſhould I obey, God or Man, judge ye?</hi> Conſcience in mans Soul is Gods Vicegerent, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience wronged will reproach, whoſe reproaches are intollerable; for my part I rather chooſe that the whole world ſhould defame me, than my own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience accuſe me; for Conſcience is a boſom Friend, and conſequently if a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63529:15"/> Friend a moſt ſweet and intimate, if enraged, it is an enemy, from which there is no flying, it will purſue a man in every place, company, action, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one Chriſtian that expecteth ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> can act that which another profeſſing the ſame Faith cannot, let them not cenſure, bite, and devour each other; this is the temper rather of <hi>ravenous Woolfs</hi> than of <hi>Chriſts Lambs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sir, my Reſpects and Service to you, craving your Acceptance of this poor, but I can ſay well-meaning Epiſtle, wherein as I have ſaid, ſo do I reiterate, that Unity is the way for our Church and State to flouriſh; it promotes the twiſted Intereſt of Gods glory and our good; it plucks down Satans Intereſt, and Popiſh Plotts and Projects it diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth greatly: And if ſtill we will have no regard to the <hi>Commands of the Goſpel, to the Love of Chriſt, to the Fellowſhip of the Spirit,</hi> which is Love, which work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Love wherever it dwelleth. If we will have no reſpect to the Glory of God in the Propagation of the Goſpel, if we refuſe to love our Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our Families,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63529:15"/> our ſelves, our own Souls) and Bodies, let us go on in Diviſions, Strifes and Contentions, but be content to ſuffer what miſeries follow, which moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will come upon us, and if God in infinite free Grace and, Mercy prevent not, be our total Deſtruction and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
            <p>Eor preventing whereof, let us unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly with one Conſent, with one Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, bear one anothers Infirmities, and endeavour <hi>to ſerve one another in Love;</hi> That this Heavenly Benediction may fall upon us, our Church and Nation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That the God of Peace, that brought again from the dead our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that great Shepheard of the Sheep, through the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant, make us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in every good Work, to do his Will, working in us that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight, thorough
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63529:16"/> Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for Ever, and Ever.</q>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <salute>So heartily, <hi>Sir,</hi> deſires and prayes,</salute> 
               <signed>Your ſincere and Willing Servant, <hi>A. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
